"Hello everyone and welcome
to English and my name is Marco.
" "My name is Catherine
and today we have an
intermediate level lesson
about education and university.
"
"That's right, today we're
trying to find a university.
We want to get some information about how
much it costs and all that sort of stuff.
So why don't we jump into the
dialogue and see what's going on today?"
I've never heard of
M-Line College, could you?
Of course sir, let me
give you a brief overview.
M-Line College is located in
the center of New York City.
The school covers a
wide range of academic
subjects and 80% of the courses are
transferable to other state universities.
And last year M-Line
College was ranked number
one in terms of graduate
and employment.
"Interesting and what
about the tuition fees then?
" "You'll be looking at somewhere
around 15,000 US dollars per semester.
" "Okay, well... " And did I
mention our on-campus housing?
Students can stay in our newly renovated
dorms for as little as $3,000 per month.
Sounds good!
Well, I'll just grab one of your flyers.
"Sir, you got the wrong flyer.
Sir, sir!"
All right, we're back, so now let's take a
look at some language on language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
So first up, Marco,
we've got this word
transferable in the
dialogue the representative
from M-Line College
said that 80% of the
courses are transferable
to other universities.
Okay, so before we talk about
transferable, what is the difference here?
We have two words, college and university.
So why is he saying
that you can transfer your
courses from M-Line
College to another university?
Well, college and
university are words that we
use in English to
describe higher education.
That means education after high school.
And a college is usually
just for bachelor students.
Students who are doing their
first four years out of high school.
But a university is
usually a larger institution
that has bachelor's
degree students as well
as master's degree
students and PhD candidates.
And so while a college is for 18 to 22 year
olds, a university can have students of all
ages who are doing sometimes very
advanced degrees, like postdoctoral work.
Okay, very interesting.
So this is why the person
mentions that 80% of the
courses are transferable
to other state universities.
So transferable means that you can transfer,
you can move to another university.
So everything that you've
studied, you can take with you.
That's right.
So a lot of people
like to start at a college
or vice versa, like to start at a big
university and transfer to a college.
And so it's important to know that
your courses can be transferred as well.
So if I studied Spanish
for two years, I can
transfer that, I can transfer
those courses to my new school.
Right.
So you don't have to start over?
Okay, very good.
And well, obviously
one of the big questions
when you're picking a
university is the tuition
fee.
So tuition is the amount of money it costs
to attend a university for usually a year.
Tuition fees is the actual
money you have to pay.
So you can say I can't afford
my tuition fees this year.
So I will be getting a part-time job.
Okay.
And so this is what tuition fees are.
In school, you call it tuition.
You don't say how much it costs.
You ask, what is the tuition?
What's the tuition?
Exactly.
Okay.
And he mentioned that it was
around $15,000 per semester.
So this is interesting.
Is this the year?
No.
A semester is half of an academic year.
Mm-hmm.
So an academic year is usually
September to May or June.
And a semester is half of that.
So first semester or
fall semester is the
study period between September
and December or January.
That's right.
Okay.
So basically what we
could deduce is that
this university costs $15,000 per
semester or about $30,000 per year.
That's right.
Okay.
Very good.
We've mentioned about
the on-campus housing.
All right.
So on campus is pretty straightforward.
It means that this housing option
where you live and sleep is on the campus.
And a university campus
is not one building.
It's many, many buildings together.
Sometimes there are classrooms and there
are laboratories and there's a cafeteria.
But there's also housing.
And most housing comes in one style.
What's the style they
mentioned in today's dialogue?
A dorm.
Because where
university students usually
live, if they live on
campus, they have dorms.
So dorm is short for dormitory.
And it basically means
that it's an apartment
building for students or
even sometimes workers.
That's very close to where
they'll be studying or working.
So the difference, what is the difference
between a dorm and an apartment?
Well, I can give you an example.
Some dorms are very fancy, but my
dorm at university was very simple.
So I lived in one
bedroom with another girl.
There were two beds and no bathroom.
And so everyone in
that floor of the building
shared bathrooms and
the bathrooms were, you
know, there's six showers
and four toilets or whatever.
Okay.
Very good.
Yeah.
I think this is the main thing with a
dorm is usually you don't have a kitchen.
You don't have usually a your own bathroom.
And so it's just
basically a room and a
bedroom and then you share
everything else with those people.
All right.
Very good.
A lot of great things related to college.
I think this is very
good vocab for you,
especially if you're
considering going to college
or something like
that, especially if you're
considering going to college or
maybe you want to continue your studies.
So why don't we go back.
Let's listen to this dialogue again
and we'll be back with fluency builder.
I've never heard of M line college.
Could you?
For a sir, let me give
you a brief overview.
M line college is located in
the center of New York City.
The school covers a
wide range of academic
subjects and 80% of the courses are
transferable to other state universities.
And last year, M line
college was ranked
number one in terms of
graduate and employment.
Interesting.
And what about the tuition fees then?
You'll be looking at somewhere
around 15,000 US dollars per semester.
Okay.
Wow.
And did I mention our on-campus housing?
Students can stay in our newly renovated
dorms for as little as $3,000 per month.
Sounds good.
Well, I'll just grab one of your flyers.
Sir, you got the wrong flyer.
Sir.
All right.
We're back.
So now let's take a look
at these three phrases
we've picked out for
you on fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
So again, when the person who was speaking
for this college was describing it, they
said that the school covers a
wide range of academic subjects.
Now this phrase, wide range is something
you'll hear in a lot of different contexts.
What does it mean, Marco?
That's right.
It means that they have a variety,
a very big variety of subjects.
So they don't only focus,
for example, on business,
they may have arts, they may
have engineering, business, et cetera.
So if you're studying
at a university and
they offer one course, they offer
English, is that a wide range of subjects?
No, no, that's not a wide range.
So basically, a wide
range of subjects would
be that you can have
many, many, many choices.
OK.
Well, after that, we also had a great
phrase when we were discussing tuition fees.
So the visitor asked, what
about the tuition fees?
And the answer was, you will be
looking at somewhere around $15,000.
Now, you will be looking at is a
very, very strange phrase, right?
Well, it's not strange, but it might sound
strange to non-native English speakers.
It's actually a very common phrase,
especially when you're talking to salesmen.
They don't want to say you'll have to pay,
or you have to pay, or anything like this.
They'll say, well, you'll be looking at
somewhere around $15,000, and that means
you are expected to pay
this amount of money,
but they don't really say
pay, so this is the key thing.
All right.
So this is the price.
This is the price tag,
and this is something
that you're saying,
salespeople say, so that
you don't have to say, well,
the price of this is $30,000.
So another good context
for this phrase would
be like a car dealership
if I'm buying a car.
And I see a beautiful new Ford Mustang,
and I say, well, how much is this cost?
What would you as the car dealer say?
I'll say, well, you'll be
looking at around $30,000.
Oh, I don't know.
That's right.
So this is a way of
saying you'll have to pay.
And well, the guy wasn't really convinced.
I think it was kind of expensive because
dorms were also $3,000 per month.
So he was like, well, sounds good.
Well, I'll just grab one of your flyers.
All right.
So this phrase sounds good is something
that English speakers use all the time.
I personally use it very, very often.
And it's another way of saying, OK, yeah.
So if you agree with
someone, you say, sounds good.
So should we meet at
seven for the movie tonight?
Yeah, sure.
Sounds good.
All right.
It's another way of saying,
yes, good, OK, very well.
That's right.
So sounds good.
Great stuff.
Why don't we take a break?
Let's listen to everything one
more time and we'll be back in a bit.
I've never heard of Amline College.
Could you?
Of course, sir.
Let me give you a brief overview.
Amline College is located in
the center of New York City.
The school covers a wide
range of academic subjects.
And 80% of the courses are
transferable to other state universities.
And last year, Amline
College was ranked
number one in terms of
graduate and employment.
Interesting.
And what about the tuition fees, then?
You'll be looking at somewhere
around $15,000 US dollars per semester.
OK.
Well, and did I mention
our on-campus housing?
Students can stay in our newly renovated
dorms for as little as $3,000 per month.
Sounds good.
Well, I'll just grab one of your flyers.
Sir, you got the wrong flyer.
Sir, sir.
All right, so universities
in the United States,
they have a very-- they have their
infamous for being very expensive.
That's right.
And so we discussed the
difference between colleges
and universities, but I
think it's important to also
talk about the difference
between public and private schools.
Public schools are
schools that are paid for
by the government
or that are subsidized.
So the government pays part of them.
And these are schools that tend
to be cheaper than private schools.
So private schools can be as much
as $50,000 for one year of study.
So for example, the famous ones like Harvard
or Stanford, those are private schools.
Those are private schools.
But the University of
California is a public institution.
The University of Illinois, for
example, is another public institution.
So there are many different
options in the United States.
I think usually the state universities
have the name of the state in them.
So University of Florida is
probably state university.
That's right.
We have to be careful,
because the University
of Pennsylvania is
a private university.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
It's an Ivy League school.
So it's one of the oldest
schools in America,
and it's like Harvard or Yale.
It's very, very high quality.
This is something that they always
mention when talking about
universities in the states.
They always say it's an Ivy League
school, just like you said right now.
What does it mean if a
university is Ivy League?
Well, league is just a group, right?
And so some of the first
universities in the United
States formed this group
called the Ivy League.
And I think it used to do-- it
used to have to do with the sports.
These teams would play each
other in sports, but I could be wrong.
Anyway, these were in the 18th century.
These were schools for men.
And there were seven, I think,
seven Ivy League schools for men.
And then there were the
sister schools for women.
Well, the Radcliffe, these
are the sister schools.
And so nowadays, both men and
women can go to all these universities.
And so we just talk about
them as the Ivy League schools
that are most famous
are Harvard, Yale, Brown,
the University of Pennsylvania,
Columbia, things like that.
So talking about universities and colleges,
I have heard also the community college.
Yeah, that can be a lot more affordable.
That's something that's--
because it's community college,
it's usually something you
go to back near your home.
Because colleges and universities sometimes
people travel very, very
far to go to these schools.
But community colleges are available
to people in your own community.
And you can take night classes.
You can do a lot of
different things at them.
They're great resources.
They're a lot more
affordable than other schools.
And a lot of people like to go to them
because they don't have
to pay these expensive
fees for housing like
dorms or for travel.
And they're a great option for people.
So community colleges and
universities are the major distinctions.
There is a lot to talk
about on this subject,
especially if you're
a student or you're
a professional considering
doing a master's abroad
or you want to go to the
stage or Canada to study.
There's a lot of things
to take into consideration.
So this is a great topic.
We really want to hear from you if
you have any other questions or doubts.
You can always find us at EnglishPod.com.
I hope to see you guys there.
Until next time.
Bye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]